## Monica Maheshwari

Learning & Development Trainer

Mb: (+91) 9920486347

Email id- monica.p.maheshwari@gmail.com

LinkedIn- Monica Maheshwari



A specialized behavioural and process facilitator, content creator, effective collaborator, motivational speaker, and a seasoned community worker with an enterprising spirit of more than 9+ years of enriched training experience in various industries and business verticals, and more importantly very enthusiastic about taking on challenging projects.

## **Key Areas**

- Talent Management
- Social Responsibility
- Learning & Development

- Engagement & Communication Interventions
- Business Partnering
- Graduate Training Programs

## **Speaker Sessions**

- On Women Empowerment organised at Al-Cogito
- Personal Branding at Cauvery College for Women
- "Rock your LinkedIn profiles" at ISTD
- Goal Setting and Influencing techniques at VIA, Nagpur

## **Pro Bono Welfare Projects**

- o Fronting PhilComm Club creating awareness on varied social events.
- Actively working on passion project 'JUNOON' working around the subject of Women and youth empowerment whereby anchored careers of more than 12 Individuals.
- O Associated with Aasmaan Foundation on certain Scholarship and skill enhancement projects.
- Worked with SAMVEDNA on certain Aangan Wadi projects in North Ahmedabad.
- Participated as Facilitator for a 2month project named Teach Indian Campaign organised by Times of India Group, Nagpur.
- Official College Jockey for a year at 94.3 My FM representing cleanliness awareness drive amongst youth.

# **White Paper Presentations**

- ISSN 2277-7067 'Welcome all, respect all'- an employee retention strategy of giving respect and replicating
  in inclusive management pedagogy.
- ISSN 0972-7175 'A study on significance of emotional intelligence for the effective leadership.'

## **Work Experience**

## **Assistant Professor (Training and placement)**

Narayana Business School, (Jul 2020- Present)

Ahmedabad

- Designing and facilitating varied Graduate Training Programs.
- Mentored 1800+ Students from Onboarding to the Final Placement.
- Discovered the 12-step placement process, coined as NEEP, instrumental program in making the candidates market read.
- Implementing and executing learning resources including case studies, toolkits, curricula, training programs, etc.
- Conducting Workshops for in-house staff and other corporate through Management Development Programs.
- Harmonizing with the management on robust campus recruitment process.
- Planning and engaging with corporates for strategic activities including guest lectures, panel discussions, conclaves, workshops, student trainings, competitions, etc.
- Liaising with companies to foster summer internships and placements.
- Working closely with Management in terms of Marketing strategies and Business Development activities.
- Spearheading projects that could position the Management institute on varied Social Media Platforms.

#### Cocreator

Business Learning, (Feb 2018- Jul 2020)

Ahmedabad

- Collaborated functional roles like strategic marketing, content and client management.
- Engaged with 43+ Clients (Academic and Corporates) trained team on execution of the Game Modules.
- Configured and designed creative tailor-made Gamification training modules.
- Engaged and aligned with 280+ B-schools with varied Training assets.

- Managed leadership effectiveness and career development programs by planning workshops, iterating training modules based on feedback and improving client experience.
- Worked upon various business strategies to bring the product close to the PMF (Product Market Fit).

#### **Director**

## Analytics edge consultant Pvt Ltd, (Dec 2016- Present)

Pune

- Created and Executed need-based Training Programs for varied Corporate Stakeholders.
- Worked with clients and their department heads and trainees delivering sessions through analysis, performance indicators and feedback sessions.
- Identified Capability Gaps and drive upskill Learning Strategies for the clients.
- Created blended learning sessions focusing on improving behavioural capability, resulting into feedback of 95% satisfaction.
- Evaluated Training Program using Kirkpatrick's model of Training Effectiveness.
- Crafted Training modules that reduce instructor 'talk-time' to incorporate more client- centred classroom atmosphere.

## **Assistant Manager**

Sun capital advisory Pvt ltd, (Jan 2015- Sep 2016)

Mumbai

- Planned and implemented workshop for 25+ Sales Representative supported the Business Development team ensuring the execution of applied learnings.
- Detailed KSA analysis of varied Team Performers.
- Strategized Market diversification plans developed training modules for the newly joined freshers.
- Designed and launched learning activities, enhanced learning culture and successfully improved utilization rate
  of learning resources.

### **Associate, Risk Analytics**

Dun and Bradstreet, (Dec 2013- Jun 2014)

Mumbai

- Worked as onshore associate for India's the largest credit bureau called CIBIL, a part of TransUnion.
- Accountable of gathering and integrating database relating to individual consumer and non- individual entities from respective financial institutions.
- Evaluated and validated the authenticity of data according to the required bureau norms given.
- Managed and Liaison with Operational team for any queries of members and provide the solutions
- Worked as a data acquisition manager testing and validating the authenticity of the database of various MFIs, NBFCs, National Banks, RRBs,
- Supervised gathering and integration of databases relating to the individual consumer and non-individual entities from respective financial institutions.

### Assistant

State bank of India, (Jan 2011- Aug 2013)

Akolo

- Efficiently oversaw all aspects of branch operations, including paying and receiving transactions, regulatory compliance, and Bank Policy & Procedure
- Managed Branch operations, and regulatory compliance, authorized and evaluated overdrafts and loans
- Investigated and resolved special account inquiries including legal transactions
- Exhibited strong probing, communication, analytical, problem solving and decision-making skills to effectively uncover and resolve complex customer and employee issues

## **Major Training Projects**

## Hitachi Hi- Rel Power Electronics Power Ltd

## 3months | On-Site | Ahmedabad

- o **Issue:** The Operations and the supply chain management team were facing a big-time challenge in adapting to the globally accepted compliances of communication.
- Need: It was observed that the employees lacked the Business communication skills and hence there was a loss of transmission of crucial information.
- O **Tools:** AV method, Gamified learning techniques, case study driven models, Real time work evaluation and continuous counselling of the employees on varied profiles.
- Objective: Train the engineering team on interaction with global clients and develop a process for erroneous transmission of the pivotal information.
- Result: The skills were acquired and executed in phased manner across a period of 3 months.

#### Rossari Biotech Ltd

#### 2months | Remote | Ahmedabad

- o **Issue:** The business development team had challenge in negotiating the deals. They were not able to handle the complexities of critical clients.
- Need: As the company had product lines that range for varied industries. Handholding client specific query was crucial.
- Tools: On-job training presentation, Observation and Feedback Model, Follow up strategy, Kaufman's Levels of Learning Evaluation
- Objective: To build confidence and make them capable enough to perform and resolve client queries and pitch potential ideas to them.
- **Result:** Resultant the individuals developed strong lens on driving simplicity and scalability. They became more self-capable to handle the pivotal clients without senior management involvement.

## Al Cogito - COGITO Corp

One Day | On-Site | Pune

- lssue: The team was newly appointed as the company had initiated the Indian operations recently.
- Need: After 6 months due to virtual work mode, the team had a big-time challenge in handling the work- life
  effectiveness.
- Tools: Storytelling, engagement strategic tools, Research based positive psychology assessments.
- Objective: The management wanted that the team should get a better understanding about their associates and their expertise, their workmates personal and professional traits.
- Result: The session ended up wherein the employees opened up about the challenges that they facing as Individual and as Professional. This gave the management a better understanding in designing the organisation's work policies.

### Swati Procon Pvt Ltd.

1month | On-Site | Ahmedabad

- o **Issue:** The Company wanted to identify the competencies of the site project team and develop them to prepare for the upcoming expansion plans of further site projects.
- O **Need:** The employees were accessed through real time on job performances. A combination of various tools and techniques were administered to evaluate the competencies of the employees.
- Tools: BEI (Behavioural Event Interview), Written Presentation on Aligning to Organizational needs, Discussing strategies on spiralling demand for varied site projects of the company.
- Objective: To identify the key performers that can be pivotal in leading the upcoming projects.
- Result: Varied competencies of the trainees were uncovered, and the management was able to define the roles based on the assessment outcomes.

### Indian Institute of Management (IIM)

3 day | On-Site | Bengaluru

- Objective: Various management students from in and around the world were shortlisted for a Vista Annual Knowledge fest event of the Institute. The challenge was to give the students a business learning experience.
- O Challenge: To identify the best among the top selected participants of the event.
- O Tools: Gamification Business Simulation software
- Result: Though students couldn't crack the game successfully, but it was an immense learning exposure for them. They understood the complexities of running a real- time business scenario.

# **Other Workshops**

- Personality Assessment
- Personal Branding
- Influencing Techniques
- Sales Training Programs
- Personal and Professional Grooming
- Business Storytelling
- Resume Building Expertise
- IELTS Training
- Presentation Skills

- Communicating for Business
- Customer Service & Communication
- Counselling for Effective Team Management
- Understanding Leadership qualities and Team
- Effective Interviewing Skills
- Leadership and Supervisory Skills
- 'In-Basket' exercises for a career in Marketing.
- Effective Team Bonding Sessions
- Professional English Training

### **Education Qualification**

- PhD (Skill Gap study), Pursuing Jan 2022
- Post Graduate Diploma in Training and Development, Pursuing 2022 (18 months)
- MBA (Human Resource), 2012
- Post graduate Diploma in Business Administration, 2010
- Bachelor of Computer Science, 2009

# **Certifications**

- Indian Society of Training and Development (ISTD)
- The complete Instructional Designer Course
- Art of Business Storytelling
- British Council certified IELTS Trainer
- Data Analysis through R

# **Technical Expertise**

R studio, Java, Oracle 9i, Advance Excel